this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
sea radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
Andy uh welcome to this show thank you
to get started let's set some context
about how this is different from data
observability so can you tell what
observability means in the AI ml space
and how that is different from just
observability in general for a genetic
software
so when it comes to General software
observability people often think of
companies like datadog New Relic Splunk
and open source technology like
Prometheus grafana so those pieces of
the software obserability stack are
designed around application performance
monitoring and the reason that it's very
different from data observability and AI
observability is that you're focusing on
different ways of measuring problems a
specific example is when you look at
time to process a web request in the
context of software monitoring you
probably want to monitor things like
average latency the P99 latency of your
request processing Pipeline and it's
very specific to a specific metric
whereas in the space of data and ml
observability you tend to deal with a
lot more dimensions and what I mean by
Dimension just basically you think of
them as metrics web in a more kind of
what we call high card cardinality in
this space to make it more specific is
when you look at a data set like a table
in a SQL Warehouse or the input into a
machine learning model you see a lot
more fields and each of these fields
would have their own metrics things like
you know if they're numerical features
you can look at the median value or you
can also look at the distribution of
these values so from the kind of
dimensionality angle there's a lot more
signals in the space of data and ml
obserability the other angle is how this
metric change in terms of behavior in
case of software I would say is a lot
more predictable in terms of how metrics
would change typically you can correlate
it with like traffic to the website or
the size of your container in terms of
CPU and memory usage but in context of
data and ml observability all the data
is actually coming from various sources
typically from either a business source
like your partner team or it can be
something like human incorporated as in
people write their own custom logic to
say take the sales number and and then
try to do some transformation to do some
prediction or it could be from The Real
World by human behavior and this is
actually a big problem for the the
machine learning world where people
Behavior change in real life due to
external factors like weather like on
hot day people probably don't go to the
maybe people will spend more time in the
mall and your camera feed will see a
different pattern compared to a colder
day for example so those external
factors are not managed by the people
who deploy software or machine learning
and therefore the possibilities of these
signals misbehave is really what I would
say not higher but really hard to
capture especially when you deal with
the signals across a large number of
features or columns so that's the
biggest challenge that we see when it
comes to this and specific example think
about like when you make a purchase on a
website and your credit card goes
through a fraud detection model that has
to get fed a lot of signals including
your IP address geolocation
shipping address all of that get run
through these models and those signals
can change underneath the hood because
say covet changes people behavior and
people purchase a lot more toilet paper
and maybe if the model has never seen
that before I probably think there's
some fraudulent activity happening here
so those are the examples that we're
trying to capture in this space is that
not just underlying software-driven
Behavior but also trying to understand
changes in extraneous factors outside of
the machine learning or the the software
development space that makes sense in
traditional software I guess failures
are predictable in terms of it's either
in your application or maybe it's in
your infrastructure and maybe just
turning your whole stack off and on
again might just fix the problem if You
observe that it is failing in machine
learning the way that you've just
described it it seems like there are
more failure modes there external
factors or internal factors can you shed
a little more light on what sort of
failure mods do you see in the AI ml
space and how does observability bridge
that unknowns that you might see in this
space to be able to diagnose and debug
problems yeah so before we start while
Labs we did a big kind of survey across
various Emma practitioners around
machine learning model failures and what
we found was that 70 of production
failures when it comes to machine
learning revolves around data and more
specifically you can think about the
semantic of data for example you take a
particular feature like in our case for
example the currency like the value of a
purchase an upstream system produces new
thing about like money as a
straightforward thing but in the lab
system they have coded in different
forms right some system coded in the
form of dollars and the other system
calls these values as sent and they
typically have to be reconciled somehow
and this value can then disagree if you
use the dollar value a sense and vice
versa and a lot of those are actually
business logic Incorporated somewhere by
someone as a kind of like business logic
owner they're not necessarily software
developers or machine learning engineer
and those things can change Upstream
without informing the team that actually
owns the model that reads these data
sources so that is like internal
business logic change and the other one
is that when external traffic change I
mean I gave an example of from detection
in the context of covet so just data
pattern behavior changes based on human
factors and those are really hard to
capture in general like even when that
happens the best effort is more more
like the monitoring in this context is
more like best effort so you don't just
look at the input data the data that
flows through them into the model but
you also want to look at the Model
Behavior itself and monitor for not
necessary failures but shifts because
the data check coming in changing the
shift in Model Behavior can change and
depending on whether these models are
going to affect the business kpi
typically we don't talk about like
that's not really especially in the AI
space it's really hard to really say
your model is failing unless you're
talking about some various obvious
metric but a lot of the time it's more
like you model is slowly drifting away
from the expected behavior and that slow
drift over time is fundamentally hard
and painful for human to know this so
typically over one week it doesn't look
that bad but if you look at that shift
over time it's called model drift or
basically just drift in general concept
and model drifts over time and you look
at business kpi that's when you detect
failures and sadly these are not
necessarily obvious to monitor until
your bottom line with kpis are impacted
so you want to put multiple defense here
at multiple layers from the Model
Behavior level but you also probably
want to do something with the business
kpis and that just makes this problem
again a little bit more complex because
these signals arrive at different time
but then you have to crawl it over time
for example yeah let's dig into that
concept drift a little bit can you give
an example application and how do you
know that it is drifting from whatever
is the ideal output because I guess
maybe if you are looking at something
like a recommendation system it's really
hard to Define when your model is
drifting so can you tell us what is
methods to detect drift how do you
define drift in different applications
or different examples so the way we
think about drift at least when it comes
to a data and machine learning
monitoring as a genetic genetic holistic
angle and that model specific technique
by the way is that we want to scan the
for drift signals across as many signal
as possible and again this is very
different from traditional IPM where you
target specific metric here you're
trying to like look for drift in many
places as possible and hopefully you can
do some probabilistic ranking among them
to say there's a high chance of the
model experiencing drift because of
these signals and again a more concrete
example I can think of right at the top
of my head is for example in image
processing it's very common for people
to take a training data set that these
training data sets were taken from an
ideal condition with perfect lighting
and on sunny days for example and then
when they deploy that model to
production suddenly the factory changed
the lighting and now you have lighting
that has a slightly different variation
of brightness and contrast creating
different artifacts on the image or the
models what the data set that they
collected is from the summer and now the
model is running in the winter the
lighting condition also changes
significantly and we've seen this sort
of like drift because of the basically
you're taking the training data set for
a model that doesn't cover the edge
cases and finding out when these s cases
happen basically pinpointing the
possible drift events or possible out
what we call outliers to the data set
that will cause the model to drift if
you watch for these outliers it's
actually there's a term that a16z kind
of like highlights the long tail
problems when you have a lot of nice
data but sometimes there are some bad
apples mixed in you really want to the
ability to like pull out these bad
apples and examine separately and that's
a big challenge in in machine learning
and data monitoring because these data
sets are in in the move they don't stay
in the center warehouse for you to
monitor all the time especially if you
think about deployment to the edge the
data that these Edge devices are
collecting or from the types of model
collecting is massive compared to the
data you typically train the model
against so knowing when your model might
fail and finding out these outliers and
making sure they are captured in the
training data set that's how you prevent
this kind of concept drift because
basically the training data set is
showing something but in reality you're
seeing something else that is not part
of that training data set the model
machine learning so far we don't have
autonomous AI so all we got is really
pattern matching and if the model fails
to match that pattern there then then
that's how you know it's drifting of
course there are more challenging
problems like ranking models those tend
to be a bit harder to measure typically
you want to do it via kind of like a
downstream kpi at least that's my
experience working with a lot of Amazon
ranking systems it's like you don't
necessarily faster drift directly from
the model because it's really hard to
say what is a correct rank for query
result like Google is all relative like
how good it is relative so the only way
you can really measure the drift is
really like customer engagement
Downstream from the result and then
those are a bit harder problems let's
say image monitoring in a factory but
they're actually relevant in the sense
that you kind of need to put these guard
rails or what do you call we call them
Fitbit or sensors or the data across the
decision making process from the model
to any kind of business decisions
Downstream yeah I can see how it is hard
to detect drift in certain types of
problems and it makes sense to look at
business kpis as a way to detect drift
and possibly say that and I suppose
maybe that is
stretched out you don't really have that
information also readily available
perhaps as compared to data let's dig
into that data drift aspect that you
mentioned earlier you know you are
looking at data from various sources
they're all multi-dimensional I think
you have rows as many types you have
columns how do you model what you see in
training versus what you're seeing in
production across these systems what
sort of statistical things can you
collect and how do you detect data
drifting yeah that's a very good
question in terms of measuring drift
like how do you really like detect and
measure this from the statistical
standpoint and there are many techniques
to do this you can run full analysis on
the data set so what we at ylabs we
build an open source Library called
while logs and the goal of this library
is to really enable this as a
standardized way of thinking about
detecting drift at scale and the way we
do this is that we collect them for we
approach the problem from the statistic
Gathering exercise so what we do is
again you have a model with a lot of
features and you use those features
probably for training first so what you
can do is start to profile these
training data sets for fingerprints like
statistical fingerprints it's about
building for example the distribution of
numerical features as histograms of
collecting the cardinality of things
most you can do both unique like IDs or
cardinality of categorical features so
you that you know that hey today you
have 50 state but somehow the data only
has like 40 State tomorrow coming in the
data stream something is off there for
example because we want to monitor those
very basic signal and then for more
complex data problems you can also do
fancy things like for example in case of
image you can translate them into more
structured information because again you
want to be able to make these signals
actionable and communicate some level of
like it has to be operationable
actionable so you can take actions from
that and decide whether the issue has
been resolved or not so for like image
data a basic technique is to really just
run through the various like image
processing pipelines and emit signals
like RGB like color channels and
brightness and distribution of the
brightness in the image that's a very
simple way to really like translate a
complex object like an image to more
human understandable signals and if you
take it to more embedding space you can
then do things like oh monitor the
distance between your production
embeddings versus the Baseline embedding
that you train your data from again it's
all about relatives so you need to First
identify what you're monitoring or
comparing against the Baseline and the
Target and you can do this across
different stages right you can compare
your training data to make sure that
every day the training data doesn't
reform each other too much if there's a
big drift you probably want somebody to
come and take a look because
semantically they might change so once
this signals are collected then you can
run various tests like payout Divergence
so basically they take distance between
the statistical signals and the distance
can be an algorithm like looking at
histogram and overlay them and then see
their differences in the area and you
have these measurements now what do you
do next you can then get a practitioner
to come in and say does the data really
drift now you do need human in the loop
and this is what I kind of believe
strongly when it comes to machine
learning is that you do need human in
the loop because at the end of the day
the model can only captures partial view
of the world because the data set is
always going to be limited and therefore
somebody has to come in and complement
that that knowledge by examining the
data and making sure that the training
data for the next generation of that
iteration of that model captures these
problems in an adequate manner that
makes sense and statistical
fingerprinting certainly is a very
interesting way to reduce your problem
Space by effectively trying to match you
know statistical fingerprints across two
different data sets that's really cool
you mentioned earlier about guard rails
and one example that you said stood out
to me where maybe the one with currency
where you're talking about a hundred
dollars or maybe a hundred dollars
represented in cents that's going to be
like ten thousand so if you're looking
at two different data sources and one of
those data sources suddenly starts
reporting currency and cents and the
other one continues to report in dollars
this in some way seems like a drift the
statistical models of what you're seeing
your average mean all of those will look
different across these two how do you
plug guard rails how do you get out of
your model drifting because your
currency is in two different forms right
now and how quickly can you act on that
so depending on where you're putting
these guardrails if you're putting these
gut rails as part of your model training
process what you can do is first of all
doing some sort of distant test like KS
test KL Divergent test that's very data
oriented like very common drift
detection problem you detect this
currency issue very fast because the
distribution of the two things will look
similar except that the range values are
completely off like one would be like a
hundred dollars and less of in terms of
purchase value and the other one all the
distribution would fall between a
hundred dollars probably between like
one dollar value versus like 100 and you
get like from a value of 100 from the
x-axis to ten thousand so the
distribution would look completely off
and probably will have a very big
distance in any kind of meaningful
distance test that's one way or if you
want to think of more a devopsy where if
people are not comfortable with the
distance method you can even measure the
gap between the P90 value for example
and these two would have very different
P90 value those are very common but you
do need to capture the distribution in
order to calculate this so if you can do
that at training that's the best place
because then you can know that their
training today looks very different from
yesterday and maybe it's the legit
reason like your your feature store has
changed and you've updated the training
algorithm to reflect this reality and
you make sure that you have
transformation in your python code to
make sure that that might be the case
but again it's important to have
somebody come in and say yes this is a
legit change and I approve this version
or hopefully you if that's an unexpected
change your model never gets to
production but sometimes these things
slip and we've had issues where we've
seen cases where the customer like the
people who deploy the model are calling
external third-party services to get
more data for the actual live inference
an example is zip code and there's
customer is like trained the model on
five digit ZIP code which is great right
very standardized except the third party
provider change the API upstream and
started returning the ZIP code with the
hyphen with the dash and that broke the
model because the model doesn't has
never seen anything like that in the
embedding space it's doing text
processing but it still doesn't know
what it is and the way they caught it
was very straightforward it was just
through you know monitoring the
distribution of the input and so the
ability to really scan through these
signals in production fast is important
and you can also do things like live
like check per data point that only
allows you to detect outliers not really
drift or if you ignite enough data point
and depending on how fast you can
response the typical pan which is just
daily like you take a day of data and
you try to say oh does it reform either
other training data or the historical
Baseline because you do need to see
enough data in production you can't
really say oh 10 decisions were made and
it's drifted it's really hard unless
this is really off so you do need to
accumulate enough signal in production
so that's a bit of a what is and again
this is different from devops monitoring
where you want like immediately the P99
is dry rapid that's great but in machine
learning you probably want to wait a bit
to see the full distribution of
production maybe six hours maybe a day
and depending how fast you can roll out
the Next Generation although we have
seen use cases where people want to know
outliers immediately and kind of like
put a fallback into another model that
is the safe or the fallback version of
that so that's a bit more complex use
case but in general it's really hard to
detect live drift fast because you do
need you know you have to have enough
signal and that that's a 22 about drift
detection you don't want to have too
many false positives
I think you touched upon a really
interesting thing which is that you
can't really respond to these incidents
instantly as they happen in a typical
devops SRE world what does the alerting
look like in the AI ml observability
space you have observability tools
you're collecting all of these signals
at what point do you raise alerts what
kind of alerts are raised and can you
dig a little deeper into what are
corrective actions that people can take
based on these alerts so this is
interestingly enough has a lot of
overlapping with the data Ops worlds so
things like numbness of your data stream
if that value just suddenly has a lot of
nodes it can really affect the model but
then you also want to monitor on things
like drift and uniqueness or of like
frequent items what we call either the
categorical features if somehow
California's most popular state becomes
the least popular state least frequent
item in your data stream you probably
want an alert so there are different
ways of approaching this but we
typically think of them as data quality
data kind of ingestion so the data
quality that the quality of the stream
itself and then the kind of freshness
that kind of like does the stream happen
it does a stream happen at the moment in
production because your system might be
down that's a bit of a overlap of devops
there but sometimes it's also like maybe
you're seeing really old data if you
have like kind of like feature store
that sends this data is from like
yesterday built from yesterday but
somehow do you see a feature with like
data from last week then you might want
to raise on the load so there's a bit of
freshness there and then drift is a
really hard problem and I said before
drift is one of the things that you
probably want to wait a bit to monitor
like adequate time typically hourly if
not daily depending on the model most
people deal with daily but we've seen
people who want to do weekly as well
because if you use day of the week as a
feature you don't want to do it daily
because you get Monday would be very
different on Tuesday so these are the
kind of common issues that we see and
then distribution drift is very common
as well each of these have different
requirements around operational aspects
so if you talking about data freshness
people want to know immediately so it's
very close to the devops angle you take
the extreme of devops and you want you
detect it you alert customer right away
another one is outliers
as I mentioned before that besides like
monitoring the holistic data stream
sometimes you really want to capture the
outliers in the Stream just so that you
know and you can examine them in the
future and that those outliers you
probably want to do them and alert
against them in more real-time manner
but then when it comes to drift then
it's the other extreme where you want
the things to be batched into like
batches of daily or sometimes weekly or
sometimes even monthly and so these
batches dictates the frequency of the
alert and they tend to have a much kind
of like a longer SLA compared to the
freshness alert for example so those are
different requirements of the data Ops
and ml Ops monitoring system it's
actually we have a lot of use cases we
see a lot of use cases where people
deploy new model architecture and then
the latency increases or sometimes the
data Upstream changes especially when it
comes to images like people send in a
larger image and suddenly the model
takes a lot longer to respond and these
kind of performance metric kind of
overlapping with devops but tied to the
ml operation aspect you probably want to
flow them through the machine learning
monitoring system as well because you
want to tie them with like model
deployment and data changes because any
of those can trigger these devops issues
so that's another angle of fly but those
changes are critical so you would want
them to be as fast as possible then the
destination for this at the moment not
surprising is very similar to devops
like they go to slack page your duty all
the standard kind of devopsy workflows
are there different people in the SRE
worlds that you see typically in
organizations who are focused on the ml
side of things you have a machine
learning model that doesn't necessarily
sit independently by itself it may be
fit into a larger ecosystem of the
product space that some company might
offer so so you might have an SRE team
that's fronting the application but you
also have this machine learning model
and this complex integration issue where
you might see performance issues so data
drift Etc so how do you see
organizations typically dealing with
that do you have different SRE teams can
you shed some light on how different
that is and how these escalations might
work in the ml space well I actually
don't see the SRE dedicated role to the
mL of Stack maybe there's gonna be a
transition soon however we see a lot of
overlapping between the data engineering
space like the data engineering team
versus the ml engineering team right
those two teams tend to be codependent
even though they belong to different
organizations with different budget
which is a bit strange but maybe that's
where we're trying to figure out where
we fit in this space as in we as in the
ml practitioners here like trying to
really fit because we don't really
belong to the traditional SRE
space so the people who are the receiver
of these alerts and signals typically
for under three categories so far that
we often see one is data engineer so
they care about things like notice data
quality things around more like Oh
missing values or the distributions are
off and then we see like a spike in Min
and Max of very simple very traditional
data Ops metrics and then the machine
learning folks they care a lot more
about things like uniqueness of the data
stream that although that can be taken
care of the data off so there's a bit of
a overlap there and then the drift is
typically consumed by the ml team
specifically because the data team
doesn't really what I call it's an
expertise Gap They Don't Really
necessarily understand and can't really
take action against drift and a lot of
the time these drips are natural and
require retraining of the model so we
would hook into the retraining Pipeline
and trigger a new version automatically
but that is more again either Realm of
the ml engineering team some companies
do van out the general metrics of things
like how many what kind of overall
health of the system or historical
information about this what's called
Data drift count in general to the SR
team to be part of the kind of global
system Health dashboard but that is just
more like they don't really take
immediate action they just like want to
track their health over time and then
finally there's a bit of a business
operators where they care about the kpi
so they want to see the health of the ml
system and then the kpi of the business
and tie them together through some
dashboarding or to some kind of alerting
mechanism and I think maybe it's fair to
say that on the data upside they might
be serving different ml models with
different drift detection needs so how
do they respond to something where they
might not detect a drift but maybe there
is one particular ml model that says
yeah this is totally an acceptable
distribution of data whereas another
model might be okay with it does that
cause problems for either of the models
or maybe the data engineering team so
who deals with this sort of like
disparity and statistical distribution
needs of the underlying data so again it
comes back to the question of whether
the data stream is drifting whether it's
a natural drift of the data if there's a
natural drift it's like customary
Behavior changes Upstream there's
nothing that the data stack can change
like the goal of the data stand is flow
the that drive data correctly to the
right ml teams or whether is that
business owner of stream changing the
semantic of an internal business field
like the currency code for a currency
kind of handling logic if that's the
case then it's false go back to the data
engineering team to really like making
sure that things are consistent for each
of the consumer either via building a
new table or one making sure that if
this thing changed then the downstream
teams get alerted accordingly but again
you already write that the drift
problems they're typically not handled
by the data engineering team typically
they go to the ml team and then the ml
team will decide whether one questions
to take what kind of actions whether
it's about retraining the model or
sometimes it's really like you have to
build a new model because hey our model
just not working with this data anymore
would need to do something else like
read structure the neural network or
something like that or go back to the
Upstream team like real basically in the
devops well you reassign that ticket to
the devops theme the data of steam and
say hey the semantic of this field has
changed and you own the logic for this
so you need to help us address it let's
go back into different phases of like
machine learning itself right in the mL
of space you have the training you have
what you run in production and this is a
continuous life cycle that evolves and
changes based on feedback so in the
coming from an obserability space how
does it assist the training set of
requirements like how is it different
during training how do you capture
observability metrics maybe or
statistical things how is it different
during training and how does that shift
during production or is it all just the
same thing on both sides in terms of the
statistics you would want them to be
aligned because you really don't want to
compare an orange to an Apple so if
you're collecting different statistics
different ways of summarizing things you
can't really say oh this model is versus
the other model or describe it over time
so that's one thing to call out in terms
of what correct however the big
difference in terms of training versus
production is the two things one is the
scale of the data like typically
training data sets are smaller most
training is done on a single machine
machines can be really beefy nowadays
when GPU you get a lot of like
horsepower into that so you can handle
quite a sizable data set but still
failing within a single machine so you
can run a lot of Statistics locally
typically you pull them from Radio
warehousing again you can like snowflake
you can run statistical analysis there
but then once the data hit production is
about different game you know you do
batch processing that happens on
multiple nodes or I says make a batch
inference for example or even more
complex things like real-time inference
then the data moves to a container that
at a much like in terms of both volume
and throughput is a different game you
need to be fast there and then if you
deploy this model to the edge what we
see is that a lot of the time people are
pretty much Flying Blind except they
monitor some basic signals it's really
hard to monitor Edge devices and
especially to even say that whether the
model is drifting for Edge deployment or
not so what we at least with while else
what it aims to do is build a
statistical kind of standardization so
you can build that
a way to standardize metrics across your
teams and Department steps so you can do
the same thing in training or deployment
the second thing is that it's also
designed for these challenges is that
it's mergable so you can take a data
profile from training and then you can
take multiple profiles from production
and you can combine the production
profile and compare it with the training
so you don't necessarily have to run it
in a single machine or against a global
system but you can run the statistic
collection in a distributed Manner and
then run the final analysis somewhere
because you're not dealing with the raw
data it's a lot faster there because
you're looking really at the statistical
signature if I think about histograms
and trying to match them so that's the
technique that while locks for example
tries to incorporate you can also do
other things as well like sampling which
you lose some accuracy but it's better
than doing nothing for example so can
you shed a little more light on how
ylabs your solution fits into the
product is it a sidecar that sits on
your container that's serving the model
or something that observes and then
reports it back into one place or how do
you integrate these signals from various
sources so while Ops is meant to be
really a data Telemetry Library it is
the python library but you can also run
it in Java and it is built on top of a
technology called Apache data sketches
so this library was originally built by
Yahoo for web love analysis so they
built it for the ability to analyze
through billions of Records per day so
it's built into these capabilities that
I describe around merging and
lightweight statistic collection what
while else adds on top of that is the
ability to do this across the
standardized apis for data science think
about pandas data frame for example or
Spa data frame so Wireless hooks into
these interfaces and enable customers to
users to run by the sketching across the
pipelines of python and data engineering
pipeline like in spark
and finally people can opt in to store
these metric objects in multiple places
things like ml flow is a very common way
to integrate because you just you have
an artifact store so you can hook ylocks
into that very easily or you can also
just store it in a blob storage in case
you're doing in like Google cloud or
Amazon Cloud and you can also do it like
over the edge because these lock objects
much more lightweight than traditional
objects traditional data so you can just
like you can transform terabytes of data
into hundreds of megabytes so that
allows you to then collect statistics
from The Edge easily and I guess it
should be easier to process when you
have like manageable sizes and reactive
it too that's nice I want to switch
gears a little bit into explainability
this is something that people keep
talking about ml AI can you first
describe what is explainability in AIML
and then we'll get into like
observability how does that help with
respect to explainability so
explainability I think this goes back to
the problem I stated at the beginning is
when you have a lot of features and
you're feeding these features into a
model and the model make a prediction
you want to know which feature
contributes to the model decision most
think about a credit scoring model
whether it's ZIP code or is it the
person's education background or is it
their job that is the deciding factor
for this I think this explainability
goes back into things like fairness and
how we think about responsible AI or in
the context of legal framework as well
as decision making from the business
perspective as well like making sure
everyone is served equally so that's the
context of explainability what it means
really in practice is that you assign
the importance of your decision models
decision to basically a number between
zero and one to your specific features
like hey maybe that person's zip code is
like 0.2 and the person's current job
maybe years of experience is like 0.5
and something like that like and you add
them up to one basically across the
model so you can do this per prediction
so every time you make a decision you
can say oh this person the for this
particular example this is the weight of
these decisions and then for you can
also do it at Global level to say for
this model based on this testing data
set and here's the way it's the global
weight it basically kind of trying to
average them out globally and the reason
you're doing this is that if you want to
monitor the for kind of like important
features or fairness and biases then you
want to focus on these particular
signals alone like maybe your where you
are from affects your life insurance so
the state for example you want to
monitor the distribution of people
across the state values so those are the
examples that I can think at the top of
my and in terms of explainability and a
bit about fairness as well it's like how
you slice and dice and compare the Model
Behavior across different population and
once you have this framework you can
talk about how to make sure your model
doesn't drip or one particular
population or one particular segment of
your data going by what you just said I
think there are different stakeholders
it sounds like in the AI ml space we've
talked a lot about
how observability might help the data
engineers and data scientists run their
models and get that into production and
run that there's also when you talk
about explainability it seems like the
customer is also a little bit of a
stakeholder in this application this
absorbability helps surface some of
these reasons why you are seeing
something back to the customer or the
end user I think observability helps if
done right so the problem with
observability expressing machine
learning is that it gets overwhelming if
you're not careful you're just
presenting practitioners with all the
data it becomes unmanageable humans are
not designed to look at 7000 features in
a fraud detection model and try to
figure out a way to really decipher the
way it's an important so observability I
think a good observability system should
be able to surface importance signals
among the noise and then highlights
important things like for example I can
think of like a segment of the data set
that is experience adverse decision by a
model or the subset of the customer I
experienced bad customer experience like
delay shipping for because the model is
giving them bad predictions so those are
examples of how observability can by
just observing the Model Behavior and
not necessarily trying to explain
everything because explainability is by
the way it's very expensive you can run
techniques like sadly and but they are
very expensive and slow so what you
really want to observe is the kpis with
respect to these important segments or
automate that process let's say how can
we surface these problematic segments in
the data stream in a scalable way in an
automated way so that the people who are
running the model can make a decision
about that maybe that segment is of
customer is not as important to the
business and it's an explicit human
decision but it has to be a Humanity
season helped by this observability
system so automating that Discovery is
in my opinion one of the most important
part uh by good observability system you
mentioned scale as a general Challenge
and I think that is interesting when
you're looking at models that have
really high dimensional data that
they're using for training maybe you
have single rows that contain hundreds
of thousands or millions of features and
they all have their own distributions
how do you see that presentable for a ml
engineer in a way that they can actually
consume it it might not be reasonable
when you say 10 000 of your features are
seeing a drift so where do you start
when you start seeing that much noise so
how do you find the signal from this
noise when you're just looking for say
drift or statistical anomalies so this
is another very problem of like why you
can't use devops tool for machine
learning operation is because if not
careful you're dealing with a lot of
dimensionality no
and how do you address this from our
experience dealing with this sort of
large-scale problem and not just from
the number of features but also the data
volume if you're running a large can
mean like large dimensionality but can
also mean large native volume by the way
is that you want to really have a good
system that can automate first of all
you want the system to quickly automate
all these analysis around drift data
quality across these 7000 features with
minimal configuration as much as
possible you want to express what you're
looking for and of course you're going
to get a lot of noise because even like
one percent of 5000 features are
drifting it's like is it important it's
hard so you start with more like devops
angle right kind of like spread out the
signals analyze it fast and you probably
get something that alerting something or
not and then now you want to do more
machine learning specific workflows
where you feed into a signals like
important features important segments
and then have the system to really
narrow down this amount of noise and
reduce them into a more human consumable
angle there are interesting techniques
around the space like using just
monitoring just the pure drift count
over time like if your drift count
suddenly increases among many features
there's a likely big chance that your
model is like experience a sudden drift
for example so there are proxy metrics
that are designed for specific not very
specific but that designs for specific
workflows that will enable you to get
fast multiple level of like drill down
so you want to start with like the
overall things like alert count of your
system and then you can go further down
and do specific problems like drift or
later quality and then hopefully you can
locate like maybe it's the most
important signals or features based on
feature importance in the training step
that are experiencing that and you
should do something it makes sense I
heard this term AI Ops which is using AI
for operations in order to reduce the
signal to noise ratio or improve and do
you see that as a thing in the AI ml
space Also where you're using another
model on top of it that runs through
your observability signals or metrics
that you're capturing in order to help
you decide or cut down the noise and
present what's important
I mean as somebody who works with a lot
of AI model I'm skeptical of that
because it's so hard to generalize it's
not that I the problem is that all these
signals they're very they come from
different domain problems it's not just
about web application performance like
the APM space deals with a lot fewer of
these the application of AI just much
wider rather than deploying services but
maybe being biased biased here but I
don't think using AI can solve this and
another thing the reason why you can't
use another AI to solve this AI
monitoring problem is that to explain
why something is happening is really
hard using an AI model you really want
to use standardized simple statistical
tests that have to explain you know
there's a beauty in in Simplicity and
you really want to use like start with
simple statistical signals that can be
explained either by you know Tech
gaussian distribution that's a very
common technique in operation kind of by
monitoring you can apply those and get a
lot of value and reduce the noise
already without having to rely on much
more complex layers and think about the
people who consuming these signals like
the data Engineers ml Engineers they're
not necessarily the expert about the AI
Ops model that we might build so it
they're not gonna enjoy going to that
documentation and try to say oh the
model is alerting because here's a hyper
parameter and you probably can go and
force us to retrain it I don't think
that's a good customer experience for my
experience working with the machine
learning team people already deal with a
lot of probabilistic signals they want
that final model final layer to be much
more straightforward yeah that makes
sense otherwise you have a problem of
trying to figure out what's happening
with that AI model that's trying to
describe your AI model and I guess that
cycle will never never end without a
human somewhere yes so in terms of tools
how is it different compared to the SRE
World in AI observability because you
are monitoring different types of
systems as an example let's say you have
a database or some storage tier that
might have its own SRE team that has its
own monitoring visualization tools Etc
you might have another one that's
responsible for streaming data and that
team might have its own SRE team maybe
and their own visualization tools and
then as machine learning practitioners
you're really consuming from several
pieces several layers in the ecosystem
so how does the tooling look like in
terms of visualization is it different
do you plug into all of them what is
typically something that you see in the
industry now so I think you're touching
on very interesting topic there where
you talk about existing tools and frame
input and processes people have so what
we see is the trend of hooking into this
existing system so they people do want
signal from AI system being flown into
Data or new rally but only a subset of
them because again otherwise you deal
with dimensionality problems and data
and New Relic are not designed for that
they can handle that in terms of scale
but in terms of the monitoring and the
configuration experience they're not
designed using like for that particular
use case as first classes so what we see
is that the SRE folks or The Operators
they tend to consume the right metrics
things like oh the total number of drift
happening in this particular model is
XYZ or maybe somebody has to pick up the
data team something like that but in
terms of really like observing and
navigating the system of a machine
learning kind of data stream or feature
store you really need to specialize tool
and this is where why we have to build
specialized tool because you have to
visualize things like Data Drive for
numerical features or data triple
categorical features and those are not
first class citizens in data docs so it
becomes really painful for the operator
to go in there and do anything like that
and datadoc doesn't deal with things
like comparing training versus
productionization and the training
process might be happening every night
so I strongly believe in specialized
tools for different purposes and
therefore you do need to have special
tools to deal with especially ml Ops the
problem of machine learning also you
deal with like model performance metric
things like confusion Matrix that gets
annoying maybe you can do it in data doc
but yeah it's probably going to be
really a lot of like Reinventing the
wheel there where about time so do you
have any final thoughts about AI ml
observability to share otherwise where
do you see the whole field moving
towards in the next couple of years so I
think that I mean in terms of machine
learning we should not try to fight
blind I think we should not reinvent the
wheel should be on top of Open Source
existing well-proven techniques that's
why we don't just reinvent something new
we take data sketching and make it
adjusted for data science workflow in
ylocks and then the goal is to really
make it locking kind of standard among
all the ml framework so that's my hope
is that people are at least putting some
monitoring maybe you know it while else
maybe without wire locks into the ml
system as they kind once they make
deploy those model and make critical
business or customer facing decisions in
terms of the field itself I think it's
definitely interesting to see the move
towards more I wouldn't call them
real-time system but with live stream
based processing and faster the
iteration of models and even things like
automatic retraining so those are the
trend I'm seeing nowadays with talking
to customers that they need to be able
to reflect the new state of the world
faster retrain the model faster however
it's also I don't think we have a good
answer for this but really figure out
how to incorporate human as part of this
automated workflow either as approvals
or kind of like you know think about
like devops deployment you always have a
human in the loop how do we make humans
more effective as part of the AI
deployment process similar to how devops
folks have built against the principle
of cicd that's something I don't think
we have a good kind of philosophy around
because you do need standardized
monitoring standardized kind of like
guardrails to do that and that something
is not there in the ml app space so
maybe we'll get there and then alongside
with things like more real time or yeah
streaming feature stores and streaming
deployment systems then we'll need those
even more because the faster you can
deploy the easier it is to break things
and so I think there's going to be some
interesting space there and then finally
I do think there's going to be a I don't
know how it would look like but the
convergence or some sort of like a lot
of like cross pollination between the
data Ops and ml app space because at the
end of the day data is a source of
machine learning so it's really hard to
talk about one's quality without talking
about the other and then the ml system
feeds back into the data system so you
know it's kind of by the circle of like
problems getting merged by this infinite
Loop if you're not careful yeah that
sounds great Andy thank you so much for
coming on the show and talking about
observability and running AI ml operator
products and production things yeah
thank you I really enjoy the chat this
is Akshay machale for software
engineering radio thank you for
listening
thanks for listening to SC radio and
educational program brought to you by
Tripoli software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening
[Music]